Okay. So, hi everyone. Uh, welcome to
class number two. Today,
uh, today I'll be talking about tool use
for language model agents. And, uh, this
is, you know, the the most fundamental
thing about agents that, uh, you know,
makes them different from a language
model.
Um so the basic idea here is uh that
we're going to be um a tool is basically
an interface through which a language
model can invoke an external computer
program. And uh this is a language model
cannot do this on its own because it's
fundamentally a token predicting
machine. But this enables you to do you
know many many different things. So you
know you can search, you can call a
calculator, you can call a browser, um
you can call Python, you can call
arbitrary APIs and so uh the language
model kind of as you'll see the method
for tool calling is standardized but
what you do downstream with the tool
call can be very different.
So there's basically two uh benefits of
tools and all of this is from one of the
readings that I I posted on the website
if you want to go back and read more
about it. Uh this is a survey that uh I
we wrote uh together Daniel and I and
Zoro Wong, one of our our students. Um
and the first thing is extending the
ability of language models. So this is
giving language models the ability to do
something that they fundamentally cannot
do. And so this could be like accessing
information or actions that are outside
the language model's um you know action
space. The second thing is uh
facilitating the language model. And so
what I mean by this is this is something
that fundamentally the language model
can do but it's just a lot easier if you
don't if you don't require the language
model to do it.
So um can anybody come up with an
example or well I guess we already have
an example in here. So like one thing
the the language model fundamentally
cannot do would be get the time four
months ago or something like that. So
the most recent information it saw is uh
from four months ago and then its
parameters are frozen. So there's no way
it could know that without calling you
know an external function. On the other
hand, uh something in the realm of
facilitating is language models can do
math actually quite well nowadays, but
they take a lot longer than calling a
calculator to do math because they have
to do reasoning like you ask them to
multiply uh two seven-digit numbers and
it will take them a very long time to do
it where a calculator can do that really
quickly. So those are the two kind of
basic categories.
So um to go a little bit more deeply
into those uh you can do things like
look up current information um and the
benefit of this is this gives you you
know fresh evidence to uh ground your
answers uh do exact computation using
like calculators or python this gives
you the ability to execute more reliably
or and quickly than using the language
model itself.
Um other things is uh access private
states. So giving the model access to
like information about the user so they
can uh respond based on the user state
um or uh make a change to your external
environment. So this could be like
browsing or or calling an API.
So to have some examples of these um if
we think about chat GPT
uh chat GPT used to like literally just
be text in and text out when it first
came out. it, you know, the the only
thing that it could do was give you
textual responses to uh your queries.
Now, it's kind of an everything app. It
allows you to do so many different
things. Um,
so like what what are some of the
examples of things that uh you know are
your top use cases of uh of using chat
GPD now?
>> Yeah.
>> Writing code. Okay. So uh what what tool
would you need for something like that?
uh like cursor or codeex I think they
they can invoke like
>> okay but that's not chat GPT right
that's cursor or codeex yeah I mean chat
GPT like in the chat GPT interface
>> they can use blender so they they can
render blender okay things so that
that's an example of um something that
requires executing code but also like
displaying it in the appropriate format
um any any other ones that people do
yeah Just the web page generate images.
>> Generate images. Yeah. So that that's
calling an image generation tool. Any
others?
>> Yeah.
Yeah. So recommend products like a
blender or something like this. And for
this uh what what sort of tool do you
think it would need?
>> Some sort of like web searches like
Google or Amazon to find.
>> Yep. So you might need like arbitrary
web search or you might need an API that
directly links into Google or Amazon or
something like that. Yeah. Any other
like weirder weirder ones? Things you
were surprised chat GPT was able to do?
>> Yeah.
>> You can render latex quite nicely.
>> Okay. messed up files when I fix you the
PDF
>> and compile everything which is very
handy sometimes.
>> Yep. Ren, it can render latex. Well, I
actually don't know if this is a tool or
if this is just a front-end interface
thing, but it might be just that it's
rendered in your web browser.
>> Oh, it creates a PDF. So, okay. Is a
tool. Okay. Very cool. Yeah.
>> Interact
>> uh interact with like Slack or something
like that. So, that's another
specialized API. So all kinds of
different things. Um I I kind of
categorized these into a list of things
that I think are um the most uh like
typical tools and most of the other
tools can kind of be categorized into
each of these. So the first one is uh
textual responses. So this is kind of
the boring one where it just gives you
an answer. Um there's two ways you can
implement this within an agentic uh like
loop. By the way, chat GPT is is an
agent now. Uh if you're like if there
was any question about it, chat GPD is
not just a chat app. It's an agent
because it makes uh iterative tool calls
to answer your queries. So that's kind
of the definition of an agent. Um but uh
textual responses, there's two ways you
can implement these. One way you can
implement these is you can have a finish
tool that says, "Okay, I'm done
interacting with the user, so I'm just
going to finish and and output some
text." The other way you can do it is if
the agent decides to not call a tool,
you can just finish the agentic loop. So
that's kind of uh you know the the
simple u you know most obvious one.
Another extremely common one. Um so all
all of these are tools and so like
theoretically all of them can be thought
of as an API but uh just to break them
down a little bit more. Um another one
is searching the web and this is you
know pulling in information um from all
of these uh different settings. Um how
many people have heard of retrieval
augmented generation? Probably everybody
everybody who took the NLP class here uh
you know has heard of it but a lot of
people. How many people have heard like
rag is dead?
[snorts and laughter] A fairly large
number of people. So there there's been
an argument in like language model
circles that retrieval augmented
generation was so like two years ago and
like nobody cares about it anymore. My
argument here is a retrieval augmented
generation where you retrieve context
and then generate answers based on it
has become so normal that people don't
even realize that they're using it
anymore. And so um it's it's so alive
that people think it's dead. Um but uh
basically you know searching the web and
retrieving information and then
generating answers based on it is now
essentially the norm uh within these uh
these applications. Now so uh that's
another tool that's provided very very
broadly and like any chat uh interface.
Another one is code execution and so
this is uh throwing in uh you know a set
of code to do uh calculations or or
something like this. very useful for uh
computation all the other stuff we
talked about. Another common one is uh
having some sort of image generation and
uh this this is you know obviously
another very popular use case in chat
GPT. Um this one's a little bit
different because like all of the other
ones here uh that I was talking about
basically you know mostly interface with
text. Um here this is interfacing with
uh this is interfacing with images. One
interesting thing is uh you'll notice
that this is not the same thing is here.
So this is like water watercolor robot
studying in a library where the query
was actually different. And so a big
part of calling these images is actually
deciding what query to put in there. So
the language model will like really
really expand the query before it calls
an image generation API. I don't know if
you can see this anymore in chat GPT,
but you used to be able to see in chat
GPT when you downloaded the image um
that it would have like a very different
caption than the caption you gave and
you could kind of like latently see what
the uh what query the the image
generator uh sent to the generate image
tool.
Then there's all all kinds of uh you
know custom functions. So, um, like buy
me buy me bananas, uh, milk and coffee.
Um, so, you know, this could create a
grocery cart, uh, for you and call the
like Instacart API to do this. Um, and
you can basically go as wild as you want
with all these tools and and add
whichever ones you want there.
Okay, so there's a bunch of different
ways you can think about tool calling.
Um the first way you can think about
tool calling is just
you provide a list of uh 50 or 70 API
functions that the agent is able to
inter interact with and it can call
these uh APIs and if you do that
basically what you're doing is like
every step you're calling one API or if
you're doing parallel tool calling
you're calling multiple APIs or
something like this but code is kind of
a special uh API uh because code is
extremely
uh you know expressive and you can view
code as like a meta tool right so within
this we have like the bakers baked 200
loaves of bread how many loaves of bread
did they have left here this is calling
an assignment tool an assignment tool
this is calling a subtraction tool um
this is calling a uh assignment tool you
know etc etc so like essentially
Um I I imagine that a lot of people have
taken like a programming languages
course or have some familiar familiarity
with programming languages but basically
you you can express
each piece of code is a tree of these
function calls um and these uh the tree
can also be have loops and other uh
control flow in it. So it's essentially
you know a very rich way of calling uh
tools. Um and so uh you can also pull in
external libraries. So these are now the
custom APIs that you pull into your uh
pull into your system. So uh you know
now if you're calling pandas now you've
opened up all of the like tools in
pandas right
and um you know you can build your own
utility functions. So you could call uh
special purpose functions that you want
uh as well. So
code is kind of special. It's like one
of the one of the you know special
things that uh it's different from other
tools in the way that it like opens up
your ability to call tools in new ways.
And so there's actually uh research work
that demonstrates that this is very
effective. Uh right now we basically
take it for granted but this was not how
uh not how we called tools like three or
four years ago uh when we first started
uh you know building agents with LLMs.
And so the the standard then was like if
you got a a query sorry this is very
small but um it basically says determine
the most cost-effective country to
purchase the smartphone model Kodak 1.
Uh the countries to consider are the US
uh Japan, Germany and India. Basically,
what this would require you to do was uh
you would call your lookup rates tool on
Germany. Um you would call your lookup
phone price uh tool. You would call uh
convert and tax. Then you would call
lookup rates again. Then you would call
uh look up phone price and you would
step over and over and over again uh in
order to uh finally get uh finally get
the result.
But if you write code, you can just
write like a single program to perform
this. And so uh this makes it like a
much richer uh a much more efficient way
of calling tools in addition to be being
richer. And so this method called uh
called Kodak has a paper uh about it and
uh some of the core results from the
paper are essentially the success rate
goes up and the average number of
interaction turns goes down. And this is
even for tasks that didn't traditionally
require code. These are for tasks that
were like viewed as regular tool use
tasks. Um but like code is just like a
good medium uh for how you would do
this.
Um but there's a reason why people don't
use code uh programmatic tool calling
for everything. Um and it largely has to
do with um with like the level of power
that you want to give to the agent. So
code is very highowered. So it's
expressive. It gives you loop variables
and libraries. This is good. But what
could be a downside of this?
Any ideas? Ju just with respect to loops
variables uh loops and variables at
first maybe. Yeah.
>> Get stuck.
>> Yeah, it could get stuck. So it could
write an infinite loop and then you need
to have something in your system to deal
with infinite loops, right? That's uh
that's a little bit annoying. Um what
about libraries?
any problem with that?
>> Yeah, security problems would be one
thing. Also, maybe just versioning and
stuff like this, but um I'm not sure if
people are familiar with this, but one
of the major issues with agents in cyber
security right now is the agents will
pull in a library that has been
compromised. Um the agent gets
compromised and then your whole system
gets compromised. So, uh this is
something uh something you need to be
very careful about.
Um they're also uh harder con to
constrain because they have the broad
action space. So uh it's you know harder
to validate and uh get predictable
behavior. Um they also have higher
impact. So they can you know use more
disk uh sorry use more memory, use more
disk, use more CPU and stuff like this.
And so because of this um we'll talk
about this more in the safety lecture,
but like once you move to programmatic
tool calling, you need to be uh you need
to think about sandboxes and how you're
going to contain the agent and stuff
like that as well.
Um any any questions about this?
Cool.
Okay. So I want to uh talk next about
the mech uh mechanics of providing tools
and right now uh every language model is
basically pretty good at uh like calling
tools but this was not you know taken
for granted. I I think I mentioned this
on Tuesday as well. Um but basically
tool calls are um expressed as tokens
like this. And so um you know a text
continuation is the weather is sunny. A
tool continuation is uh like a tool call
and then you have get weather or
something like this within the the tool
call. And very often uh you have both in
the same uh output. So if you remember
react uh which was talked about before
um I can actually draw this on the board
but react basically you have your text
up here
and then you have your uh tool call
and then you have your tool call down
here.
Yeah, this is like the end of the tool
call.
And so now you have the the model be
being uh giving a response to the human
uh while it's making the tool call. And
then uh in here you have the like actual
tool call that it's making. And so the
react loop is no longer expressed as
like separate code. It's expressed more
as like just a single completion. um if
you're using one of the reasoning models
um
that can reason uh like have long
reasoning traces and stuff like that. In
addition, you might have like the
thinking tokens up here and then a
message and then the tool calls. And so
the thinking is like very verbose
thinking that you don't show to the
user. The text is the less verbose uh
message that you show to the user and
then the tool call is like the actual
output you have there.
Yeah,
>> the tool call tokens has to be in the
vocabulary of the model during
pre-training also, right?
>> Yes.
>> So all of these service tokens are going
to be vocabulary.
>> Uh yes. So actually that's a good point.
I said yes, but the answer might be no.
I'm going to repeat the question first.
So the question was um do these tokens
have to be in the vocabulary when you do
pre-training? Um, typically if you're
pre-training on all of the internet, you
don't necessarily have to have them in
the vocabulary yet. Um we there are
cases where you might do that but it's
actually more typical to introduce them
in a process of mid-training which is
like uh between uh it's when you're
training on like moderately large
amounts of data on things in the format
that you like and then uh you might do
reinforcement learning after that but
you might not necessarily have them when
you pre-train on the whole internet.
Cool. Um
so
I think this should likely be familiar
to um you know uh people who have
implemented things in uh previous
natural language processing or or
whatever courses. But um if you have the
chat format like the open AAI chat
format you have things like the system
message, the user message, the assistant
message and then uh these are
represented as something like JSON in
uh like in Python when you call the call
the model but these get converted into
something uh with like a special token
here the system uh like this is a system
prompt and then be concise and stuff
like this. So like each chat message
gets its own format and this is an
example of the quen format
but uh as I'll show later the other uh
other functions are in different
formats. So
tools basically um add a structure to
the request and so you have a tool
definition like this and uh this tells
you that it's a function. The function
name might be get weather. Um the
parameters are city and the type is a
string and this is required. And this
schema gets passed to for example the
chat completions function that you you
would use when calling openAI or
something like this.
So um when the prompt uh contains
something like this, you might have uh
this included in the tools section of
the prompt and then the output uh ends
up being something like name get weather
uh with the appropriate arguments like
the city of Pittsburgh.
So um we we had a question about how you
pre-train the models and um you might
not be pre-training but at least at
mid-training and beyond you will be
training the model to fit a particular
tool call format. The interesting thing
is uh every model has a different tool
call format. Maybe not everyone but many
of the different ones. And so uh Quen
has like im start tool call uh IM end.
Uh Mistall has tool calls and then uh
all of the tool calls. Deepseek has
their like DSML DeepS markup language
function calls. They they don't call it
tool calls. they call it function calls
and then evoke invoke and basically you
know any of these works. Um there might
be like minor minor differences in uh
which one gets better performance or not
if you train the same model with the
same data. Uh but
what you need to know is you need to
know that these are different. So you
can't just assume that like some parsing
code that works with deepseek will
suddenly work with quen and vice versa.
Yeah.
>> You said you add functionality.
So need to provide.
>> Um, so what do you mean by loose
generalizability?
>> Yep. fine tuning
set of
>> Yeah. So when you're when you're
fine-tuning, you will want to match like
if you're fine-tuning
from a model that's already been
trained, you 100% want to match the tool
call format. You don't want to try to
get it to do something it wasn't trained
on. Um, and the good news is this is all
implemented in like hugging face with
the apply chat template uh function. And
so you need to apply the chat template
for the model you're using, but that's
all implemented. If it's not implemented
properly, you can go in and um like it
you ask them and they'll go in and
implement it or you do it yourself or
something like that. But yeah, it's it's
all standardized now. But I I want to
people to know that this is going on
under the hood because if you don't know
this, you can make mistakes and uh and
it will not be happy.
Cool. So um once you have done this uh
the next thing is um that you
do tool call parsing and actually I'm
going to talk about tool called kernel
parsing in the next section. So um not
immediately here but like let's assume
that if uh the language model outputs
this you have a way of parsing it into
uh into the function arguments. you then
um like have the you register the tool
at initialization and um you uh have a
way to resolve it so that you get a map
from the name to the tool that you want
to execute. So most agentic frameworks
basically will will have a way that you
can add new tools. Each tool gets its
own name and then you have a Python
function or something like that. Python,
TypeScript, whatever language. And then
it uh it will be dispatched to that with
the appropriate arguments. And so then
at each time you you parse uh you look
up the tool, you validate the uh action
from the arguments and you execute uh
and then you return. But um at
validation time, this can fail if the
model gave you the wrong uh the wrong
tool call. At execution time, this can
also fail if there's like not something
that was explicitly said is bad uh is
like invalid but implicitly is invalid.
So like for example, if you have an
execute Python tool, it might accept any
string as Python, but then when you
actually try to run the Python, it it
might fail. So that that would be like
an execution error. And then if it does
if it well whether it uh whether it
fails or not, then uh you get an
observation out of it.
So this is another detail um that that's
pretty helpful but also really annoying
uh when you're implementing agents if
you if you get it wrong. But basically
each tool call is assigned an ID uh when
you uh when you run it basically by um
uh either the language model inference
code or the agent code and then you get
a result and the result has a matching
call ID and this is useful especially in
the case of parallel tool calling
because I'm going to talk about parallel
tool calling in a bit and having the IDs
matched lets you know which tool call is
associated assiated with with which
result. But the uh the problem is uh for
instance uh anthropic if you have a tool
call with no matched tool result it will
die on you and uh so it will tell you
this is an invalid history and I'm not
going to accept this history and and
generate any more outputs for you. And
so in my practical experience there's
times when for example the assistant
makes a tool call then suddenly uh your
your program dies or something like that
it fails to write out the tool result
and then you resume it it doesn't have
the result the associated result and uh
anthropic fails to fails to work for
you. So this is a little bit of a a
detail that you need to know.
Okay. So, um, any any questions there?
Yeah.
>> And, uh, great question. Are the tool
calls asynchronous? Um, I'm going to
talk about that in like the the next
next section. Yeah.
Cool. Okay. So, now now here's a very
technically algorithmically
difficult problem. Uh, that may be very
interesting to you or maybe not not very
interesting to you. But if it's not
interesting to you, be glad that other
people are solving it for you. Um, so,
uh, language models are definitely not
guaranteed to generate well-formed tool
calls. Um, and this is an example. Uh,
you can see that this is JSON that's
missing the uh, last closing bracket.
So, this is poorly formed JSON. You put
this into your JSON parsing program and
it will throw an exception and you won't
be able to get the uh, the data out of
it. So I I've seen a million people go
in and try to like figure out if the
brackets are missing and like add one
post hawk, but you don't want to be
doing that. That's not not fun. Um so
there's a bunch of constraints uh that
you uh could be assigning to each of the
tool calls. So the first one is syntax.
So it has to be valid JSON. So this is
kind of like table stakes, right? So it
it needs to parse. Um the second thing
is uh shape. So make sure that if you
have expected or required fields, you
have the required fields. Um the third
thing is types. So uh you know if you
have city, the city must be a string. Oh
sorry. Yeah. Um yeah. So if you have a
city, city is a string. Um if you have
uh values, uh you know the units are in
the appropriate units. So this can all
be expressed through um something called
JSON schema or basically any schema
library. Um so it's like this is a city
uh the type is string and the units can
be uh Celsius or Fahrenheit and city is
required.
So um the the good thing about this is
this has machine readable validation
rules. So you can check if like a call
uh follows the schema.
But um
one way that you can express whether the
schema is valid or invalid is by
defining a grammar over uh over the
schema. And how many people uh did like
contextf free grammarss or like context
or those sorts of things? Regular
grammarss. How many people know regular
expressions?
Okay. A lot of a lot of people. Okay. So
a regular expression is a regular
grammar. Um does anybody know how you
can parse a regular expression?
>> Finite state automaton. Yeah, that's
exactly correct. Um so a finite state
automaton uh for for those who are less
familiar with this is
something that looks a little bit like
this.
Um, so you have a state and every time
you take a token as input, uh, you move
to a different state. So if you get A,
you would move to this state. If you get
B or C, you move to this state. And
This this works on uh something called
uh uh regular grammarss. So regular
expressions like the the slashes and dot
stars and stuff like this that you might
use to search for search text are uh reg
are regular expressions and they can be
expressed through regular grammars. Um
JSON schema cannot be expressed through
a regular grammar. um it can be
expressed through something called a
contextf free grammar and you can uh the
context free grammar can basically make
a tree that looks a little bit like
this. So um every JSON expression can
have brackets on the side. It can have
commas between its members. Uh this can
be a string um and this can be a unit.
And if uh the JSON schema is in the
correct format, you should be able to
create a tree uh that looks like this.
If the JSON schema is in the wrong
format, you might create a be able to
create create most of a tree. But then
when you get to a unit, a unit cannot be
K. So basically this would uh this would
fail even though a unit can be K, but uh
we we defined this to not accept Kelvin
as our our unit of temperature.
So
um basically if you can parse uh the
tool call with a contextf free grammar
uh defined from your JSON schema you can
uh you can do this and I'm not going to
go into a lot of details but a finite
state automaton cannot parse a um a
contextf free grammar but there's
something called a push down automaton
that can allow you to do this. So
basically it adds a stack to uh the
regular grammar and uh you push things
onto the stack uh pop things off of the
stack and eventually can um eventually
can decide whether it's uh parsible or
not. And so what you do is you start out
at the very beginning um with uh a state
in this push down automaton and you step
through and uh validate your output as
you um as you generate it from left to
right
and I'm giving some examples from X
grammar uh and X grammar is a thing
that's actually pretty widely used in uh
all of the LM inference libraries. It's
actually developed by people in the
machine learning department here. Uh so
what you uh what this means is every
time you get an LLM predict the logits
of the next token, you take a look at
your grammar and if the grammar says
this is a valid next token, uh you get a
score of one and if you have an invalid
next token, you get a score of zero. And
you set all of the invalid next tokens
to negative infinity. um for the output
logits and then you renormalize so that
you get probability only on the valid
tokens. And so what this uh lets you do
is this ensures that you generate valid
output.
Um, and so
this is another figure from the Xgrammer
paper and they do these uh tricky things
where basically there are some
vocabulary that are always valid or
always invalid and you premputee these
and then there what there are those that
are valid only in some contexts only in
some uh stack context and then you
calculate them on the fly. So it's uh
very interesting algorithmically if you
like algorithmic uh stuff. If you don't
like it uh be glad that the people in
the machine learning department are
doing it for you basically. Um so
because of this almost always um if you
are uh if you are have this enabled you
will uh and set your appropriate JSON
schema you will get wellformed to tool
calls. So that that's uh that's great.
There's one case where you actually
can't uh uh get well-formed tool calls
despite this. Um may maybe I can give a
quick quiz. This is very very difficult.
So I don't know if anybody can get it.
But any anybody have an idea where even
this would not be uh not be enough. Need
to be familiar with uh with LMS I guess.
>> Yeah.
Uh I I think that's close enough to what
I I wanted to say. So basically um when
you run out of tokens, so models can
only generate so many tokens and you
might run into a place where you're
still on a valid path through the
automaton, but you're not at the final
state. So you generate like part of a
JSON output. So very very good. Um and I
I've actually encountered this. There's
uh theoretically a way you could do that
which is like you count the number of
output tokens that you still have left
and you you cut them off but that's uh
if if somebody wants to implement that
in next grammar as a extra credit
assignment you know be happy to happy to
have that okay so now um let's go to
rest API calling um so there's uh two
different ways to um there's different
ways to Express
tools and um I'd say probably most
people are familiar with REST APIs. The
these are the ways you interact with web
services. Um but
actually sorry there's one other way to
call APIs and one way to call APIs is
through programmatic tool calling where
basically um you just give the model a
Python program and you say use the stuff
in this Python program to call tools.
And so if you do something like that you
might have like weather lib.py pi and uh
you have the get weather function in
here uh with its city and its units and
uh then you just say call this function
whenever you need to and you give it the
ability to execute Python and it will be
able to call that tool. So in
programmatic tool calling this uh this
works but this is not um callable
remotely and it's also not callable from
the like standard method of tool calling
that you use um that you use when you
uh implement this uh not through
non-programmatic tool calling.
So there's a way to turn this into uh
REST APIs. Has anybody used fast API
before? It's a pretty common Okay. a lot
of people. It's a pretty common library.
And basically what this allows you to do
is this allows you to create a web uh
web backend uh extremely simply by just
uh setting up a fast API uh giving an
API key so you can get people to
validate against the API and then
writing a Python decorator where uh
weather becomes uh becomes this. And so
this is good uh for a couple reasons.
The first reason is maybe if you don't
want people uh looking at the weather um
then uh you can prevent them from
looking at the weather. But probably
more importantly if you don't want
people like getting your personal data
or something like that you can require
an API key and uh this will uh allow you
to block anybody who doesn't have an
appropriate API key for instance. Um the
other reason why is this gives you a
JSON schema for free. uh and when I say
for free of course you know this is
something that's implemented in in fast
API but your entire API can be expressed
as a JSON schema and that JSON schema
can then be provided as is to a language
model and that language model can then
use it uh to you know specify which
calls are allowed and so then you could
go in and process this and um whenever
the agent made a tool call you could
then send it to your API server and they
it could use that on the API server
Um,
another option for calling these is you
can just uh use the curl command. And
the curl command um basically allows you
to call these APIs uh directly like this
as well. And so if you have a a coding
agent that has access to bash, it has
the ability to um to call like this.
So this is maybe maybe reasonably
straightforward if you're familiar with
uh REST and stuff like this. Any any
questions or comments or
If you haven't played around with fast
API, it's nice. It's very easy to use.
But um the reason why I wanted to cover
this first is this is kind of like the
traditional way of of programming uh you
know before agents. Um
there's uh something called MCP the
model context protocol and this was
introduced by anthropic uh maybe twoish
years ago or a year and a half ago and
the idea was this is was designed to be
a standard way to uh give your model
additional context.
When I first saw this I actually was
like why do we need to do this? I don't
understand why we need to do this. Let's
uh let's just let our uh agents call
APIs. Um but there is one uh important
point about one one or two important
points that make MCP different from just
calling a normal API. Uh and I'll I'll
explain them here. But um first I'll
explain why I didn't real I didn't like
I thought this was not actually
necessary. And basically the reason why
is every time you set up an MCP, what
you do is you have your AI application
and then you set up a couple MCP
clients. So like maybe this is your
weather client uh your this is your
weather MCP and your uh your GitHub MCP
or something like that. So you can ask
what the weather is what the weather is
and push it to your GitHub. Um uh and
the reason why I didn't think this was
necessary originally was because like
why do you need to run a program to call
an API, right? We already have good ways
to call APIs. We just, you know, send it
to the the REST API server.
But um
okay. Yeah. So so that's a little bit of
an aside. Um, uh, I'll I'll get back to
that in a moment, but for a little bit
of an aside, uh, there's a really nice
library called fast MCP. And fast MCP is
basically designed to be fast API for
MCP. So if you want to create an MCP
server for whatever you want, you can
um, just like basically swap out fast
MCP and swap it uh, swap out fast API
and swap in fast MCP and you can uh,
create an MCP server very easily.
Um, you can also take in a spec that was
generated by like a REST API and just
turn it in into an MCP as well.
But here here's the main reason why you
might want to use MCP uh as opposed to
an API. Uh, and the reason why is
because it gives you an extra layer of
security. And so MCPs have an MCP
API key. And this MCP API key uh is
something that you need to provide to
the process that's running your agent.
Separately from this, you have the
upstream API key. So like let's say you
are getting um getting your agent to
connect to your GitHub. The upstream API
key would be your GitHub token and you
would provide that to the MCP server,
but you would not provide it to the
agent. And then what you provide to the
agent is the MCP API key, which allows
you to authenticate into the MCP server.
And so the reason why this is important
is what happens if you give your agent
the GitHub your GitHub token and your
agent suddenly decides that it's a good
idea to push that to your public GitHub
repository.
Not good, right? [laughter] Your account
gets compromised and uh you get malware
installed onto all your repositories or
something like this. So you want to give
the the agent something that is
relatively harmless. Uh so that even if
it leaks it for whatever reason like
that leak is relatively harmless and
then the um the actual credentials get
get preserved and so that was basically
the reasoning behind it.
So um just to go into a summary, they
all give you the ability to add a set of
APIs into uh into your agent. Like you
could do that through a regular JSON
schema or through an MCP. Um
the uh but a lot of other things are
different. So like for discovery um you
might need to fetch an open API uh
document. For MCP there is a special API
that allows you to list all of the
tools. Um for invocation um you call an
HTTP
uh thing here for um MCP there's an MCP
transport and this can be through
various ways. You connect through
standard IO or you connect through an H
uh uh a socket or something like that.
Uh I already talked about authentication
and um MCP actually has a few other um
has a few other like conveniences like
you can add resources, prompts and
extensions, but I'm not going to go into
a lot of detail about that.
Cool. Um
actually, um there's two other things
I'd like to mention. um there I don't
want to uh I I guess I forgot to add
them to my slide. Um so the first thing
is um MCP registry. There's an official
MCP registry. So if you want to find
MCPS uh that allow you to do something
like this, you can, you know, go to this
registry and find uh any of a very large
number of MCPS. There's also like a
million and a half uh MCP server like
websites that you can go to that are are
ranked based on uh popularity and stuff
like this. Another thing is um I've been
talking a lot about the Pittsburgh
weather and uh the funny thing is uh
today I prepared all of these slides
like earlier of course but today we
actually got Pittsburgh weather that was
simultaneously rainy and sunny at the
same time. And so I managed to break my
own API because it cannot return
multiple states at the same time. But uh
uh yeah, it was uh quite the
coincidence. You can see the torrential
downpour and the the bright side at the
same time. Okay. Uh back back to serious
stuff.
Cool. Um so another big uh kind of like
development pretty recently is parallel
tool calling. in parallel tool calling.
Um the the basic problem we want to
solve is the same problem that I talked
about when I talked about like the codec
and the programmatic tool calling which
is if you call tools one at a time. Um
the uh it it could become very long for
even a simple operation because you
might do a weather and then do a
calendar and then do a flight. Um, but
if tool calls are independent, you can
actually call them at the same time. And
this is done pretty simply. You just
like add add multiple tool call
blocks to a single agent response.
The um there's a few nuances about this.
The first one is um you can only
paralyze tool calls if they don't have
dependencies on each other. So, um, like
if you were looking up the weather for
Pittsburgh and reading today's calendar
and looking up flight status, that might
be, uh, might be good. Um, but if you
need to find a customer ID, use it to
fetch orders and refund the selected
order. Obviously, you can't do that. So,
there's limits to the parallel tool
calling you could do. And if your
calendar or your flight was dependent on
the weather, then you know, obviously
that'd be a problem, too.
So, there was a question about this. Um,
do you execute the tool calls in
parallel? And the answer is typically
yes. You can just uh use typical Python
uh syntax to you know have a whole bunch
of tool calls and then execute them and
then uh use something like
async.io.gather to uh to return the
results of them when they run in the
same time. So this is uh uh this is
pretty common. Another thing I'd like to
point out is um this is a major
difference between really efficient
language models in note efficient
language models. And
there there's this weird
weird paradox in agentic language models
nowadays that more expensive models more
expensive models can actually be cheaper
if you measure them on a taskbytask
basis. And there's two major reasons for
this.
The first major reason is more expensive
models can be smarter. So they pick like
an appropriate solution more quickly. Um
but another thing is um more recent
models
do parallel tool calling uh a lot
better. So they make a whole bunch of
calls at the same time. So if you're
using a coding agent or something like
this, uh you use the the better uh you
use the better models and they are doing
like a bunch of view images at the same
time or they're uh like writing a bunch
of different files at the same time or
something like that. That's because
they're doing parallel tool calling.
Well, um does anyone have an idea of
like why they got so much better at
this? They like this was not a huge
thing even though parallel tool calling
mechanisms have existed for a long time.
This was not a huge thing until maybe
like six months ago or something. Yeah.
>> Reinforcement learning just forced them
to do that.
>> Yes. Exactly. So reinforcement learning
uh kind of forced them to do that and so
the models were very heavily
incentivized to fish finish tasks
quickly and parallel tool calling is one
of the good ways to do that. So if you
do reinforcement learning with a very
heavy like brevity penalty on on how
long uh the task execution is, you can
get uh like a lot more parallel tool
calling.
Cool. So um the final thing I'd like to
talk about in this lecture today is
evaluating tool use. And so I'm not
going to talk about evaluating endto-end
agentic tasks immediately yet. um but
rather talk about evaluating just the
tool usability of language models
because it's kind of like a prerequisite
for language models to be good at um uh
good at agentic tasks. And there's a
bunch of data sets for this. The most
famous one is the Berkeley function
calling leaderboard and this has four
versions. Uh it started out with version
one which was basically um single turn
uh tool calling. Um it's then evolved
through the four versions and now it
covers um multi-turn tool calling. It
also does have aentic tool calling but
this is more um not for like endto-end
coding agents or something like that.
It's uh tool calling agents and they
also have tool calling robustness. So
they measure um hallucination of
arguments. They also measure format
sensitivity. So when I talked about like
the all the different formats uh they
have uh parameters about that as well.
So um
when you uh go in to evaluate the whole
uh stack there's a number of things that
you want to uh evaluate. So the first
thing is did the language model choose
the appropriate tool for the task. So it
might have picked like a an
inappropriate tool that can't uh allow
you to do that uh the task at all. Um
the other thing is arguments uh which is
uh you know whether you you add the
right values. Um if you're talking about
agentic tool calling you can talk about
whether it did it in the right order and
then you can uh measure endto-end task
accuracy for if you're doing uh agentic
tool calling. And all of these are kind
of metrics in this leaderboard.
Then separately from that there's also
um efficiency. So like uh how quickly
can you solve the task? Like um how many
tokens did it take? How how much did it
cost? Um reliability. So um you know if
a tool call times out uh does it retry
appropriately? If a tool is out of
order, can it choose a a different one?
And also um safety. So if you have
adversarial outputs where you ask it to
use a tool in an inappropriate way, uh
can you do this? And all of these are
like over the four iterations of this
benchmark. It covers uh all of these
dimensions.
Um yeah, I kind of covered that already
actually. So one other uh really
interesting benchmark uh for tool
calling is uh this open router uh tool
call air rate benchmark. I don't know if
anybody like uses open router or has
seen this before. Maybe no.
Okay. So um this is for the same model.
All of these are for uh I think this is
GLM 5.3. So it's like the same the same
model and it's measuring the tool call
error rate
simply the only thing they varied is who
serves the model to you. And this is uh
this is pretty important obviously
because you think oh I'm going to use
this model maybe you know it's going to
be the same regardless of who provides
it to me but actually the difference is
between 15% and like 0.01
to 0.05%.
Any idea uh why this might be?
There were some uh there were some hints
in the lecture and some uh not some
hints in the lecture
>> is decoding algorithms different maybe
someone's using
like cheaper version of the model or
quantized version of the model.
>> Yeah, great great points. So I'll I'll
repeat it. So number one is the decoding
or the inference algorithm could be
different and um one very big difference
is whether they're using quantization of
the model or not or like what level of
quantization of the model they're using.
So my my personal experience is um uh
FP8 models uh FP8 is kind of like the
default level of uh quantization for the
model um get a lot fewer uh mistaken
tool calls than FP4 models because FP4
is like compressing it very heavily.
It's saving money for the inference
provider, but it's it's usually a worse
model. There aren't very many FP4
quantizations that can allow you to get
the same performance. Another one was uh
speculative decoding. Um I don't think
we're going to talk about speculative
decoding a huge amount in this class.
Maybe I'll talk about it during long
context or actually may there are a few
algorithms specifically for agents which
are interesting. So maybe we can talk
about it. But basically what it is is
you have another cheaper model um that
predicts what the more expensive model
is going to do and then you use that to
like speed up your inference.
um spec lossless speculative decoding
probably shouldn't make a difference
because it it's like not changing the
underlying result of the model. But if
they're doing some sort of like lossy
speculative decoding uh then that might
might cause it to be different. But then
you know calling it the same model is
also probably a bad uh a bad idea. Uh
there's one other thing um that I
mentioned uh and anybody have an idea
this was actually mentioned in the uh in
the class today.
What can you do to make your tool calls
more successful?
>> Yeah.
>> Constraint decoding. Yeah, exactly. So
these different providers might be using
different constraint decoding
algorithms. Um just practically
many many of these providers will be
implementing their own inference
algorithm. So they'll have their own
inference algorithm completely
implemented from scratch. Um some of the
providers will be using an open source
one like VLM or SGLANG. And VLM or SG
lang support different grammar-based
decoding uh algorithms. And so uh some
of these providers just might not have
that implemented and so they're entirely
relying on the language model to do good
tool calls. Um otherwise uh they might
not. A final kind of like boring reason
why tool calls might fail is the
inference provider might be unreliable.
So it might go down some of the time and
then the tool call would fail.
Cool. Um so these are the um that that's
the main thing that I I had for today.
Um so tool use is basically a layered
system. Um you know the tools add
capabilities such as retrieval,
execution, generation, application.
They're what make an agent an agent. Uh
but we can't get that uh for free. And
um you can uh add schemas to the prompt.
Uh the models emit calls and then you
validate dispatch and match results by
ID. And we can add constraints uh like
grammar-based decoding. um they don't
guarantee semantic correctness. So um if
you have like a Python program, the
Python program might still be wrong even
if you generated uh you know a string
that could be parsed as Python. Um and
there's a number of uh ways you can
interface with them like direct rest
calls and MCPS.
Uh and then we have a lot of systems
that um orchestrate dependencies and
concurrency and uh allow us to evaluate.
So yeah, that that's uh what I wanted to
talk about for tool calling. Uh this
will be something that is covered in the
harness uh assignment or the first
assignment where you build your agent.
So you'll need to need to deal with
this. Um but and next time we're going
to talk about context management for
long context in long context LMS. But um
any questions
to wrap up?
Okay. Yeah. Yeah. And I'm going to
repeat in case people didn't hear in the
back, but the first um uh assignment for
reflecting on the lecture and talking
about something you learned in the
lecture is going to be up on Canvas. So,
make sure you uh make sure you submit
it. Thank you.